Gheorghe and Eugenia Popescu-Judetz collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series I: 1990-1996 Accruals
  - Music Transcriptions
    - Musical arrangements, 1949-1969, Fifty sets of 9 1⁄2 x 14 bound and unbound, multiple-leaved sets of sheet music (Box 9-10, Folder 24-31)
      Arranged numerically in the collector's order. Contains holographic harmonizations and scores created for performances by Ciocîrlia and Perinitza Ensembles. Each score has a title, composer, and often the date of composition or transcription (in Romanian). See Folder 6 for inventory.
  - Dance Notation
    - Field notebooks-dance notation, 1950-1970, Forty-six bound (hard- and soft-covered) paper notebooks, predominantly 5 3/4 x 8".
      Arranged numerically in the collector's order. Used by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz in the field. Contain his handwritten notes, dance notations, sketches, etc. (in Romanian). Contributions occasionally made by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz. See Folder 7 for inventory.
    - Dance notation books (Box-folder 16/32)
      One copy of Judetz Folk Dance Notation, created by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz. Edited and revised by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz and James Rocevic. Pittsburgh PA: Duquesne University Tamburitzans, Institute of Folk Arts, 1979. GV1587.J82. Bound, paper-covered publication that explains the Judetz dance notation system. Includes notation exercises.
      Popescu-Judetz, Gheorghe. Brîul (Dance on Belt). Bucharest: Editura de Stat Pentru Literatura si Arta, 1956.
    - Dance notation files, 1949-1952, Thirty-three files of 8 1/4 x 11 3/4" paper sheets of dance notation and description (Box 16-24, Folder 33-156)
      Mic Dictionar al Jocurilor Populare din Zonele Folclorice Neamt si Bacau (trans., Small Dictionary of Folk Dances from Neamt in Bacau District). Originals and photocopies. Arranged numerically by file number in the collector's order. Prepared by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz. The bulk of the material is handwritten dance notation, from sketches and rough drafts through publication-ready final versions. Descriptive information may include name of dance/variant, place, informant, and date. Dance notations usually grouped by region or dance type. Files also contain choreography for performances, including staging diagrams; a manuscript of an ethnographic description of a wedding ritual (23 pages); a manuscript of a glossary of dances from Bicaz, Moldavia (421 pages); and classifications, diagrams, and analyses of rhythm and meter patterns (in Romanian). See PDF copy of inventory.
  - Dance Index
    - Index cards, 1950-1970, Eight stacks of 6 x 4" sheets of paper containing information on individual dances. (Box 25-26)
      Arranged numerically in the collector's order, with several groupings by geographical region. Created by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz, with some assistance from Eugenia and others. Primarily based on information collected in the field and documented in sources listed above. For the most part, each sheet contains handwritten or typed information on a single dance type, including variants, locations, and other descriptive information (in Romanian). The eighth stack (Box 26) consists of two-sided 8 x 11 3/4" sheets of thin paper, each containing handwritten copies of multiple index cards that since have been destroyed.
    - Listing 1, 1965-1970, Bound, alphabetically-tabbed 8 1⁄2 x 11 3/4" volume (Box 27)
      Contains list of more than 4,000 dance names. Within each tabbed section, dance names and locations are listed in random order (in Romanian). Handwritten by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz. Primarily based on information collected in the field and documented in other sources in the collection. Contains notes on informants and so forth in the back.
    - Listing 2, 1954-1956, 34 pages (Box-folder 28/167-168)
      Manuscript listing of dances from Bicaz, in the Moldavia region. Typewritten with handwritten corrections (in Romanian). Based on materials collected in the field 1954 to 1956 and documented in other sources listed above. Dances indexed by name, place, and variants. Created by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz to accompany unpublished volume on folk dances from the Bicaz area (see Folders 113-136, 174-178).
    - Listings 3-4, Two sets of paper sheets (one 8 1/2 x 11 3/4" and one 6 x 8 1/2", respectively) (Box-folder 28/169-173)
      Contains drafts and worksheets of dance listings from all regions. Handwritten by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz (in Romanian).
  - Graphs and Maps, Two multi-paged, bound, handwritten graphs and three hand-drawn maps (Box-folder 28/174-178)
    Contains analyses of dances from the Bicaz area (originals and photocopies). Prepared by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz to accompany the manuscript on folk dances from this area (see folders 113-136, 167-168). The graphs depict characteristics of 213 dances (such as formation, positions, function, location) and the frequency by location of 90 dances, respectively. The maps portray 1) the "interference and circulation" of dances (transmission and dissemination), 2) the transmission of one dance type (ardelesc), and 3) zones of "interpenetration" (influences from other regions).
  - Scenarios, 1960-1964, Two handwritten manuscripts (Box-folder 28/179-180)
    Describing scenarios for two stage productions by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz (in Romanian). The Dobrudja Suite scenario was created in 1960 for the Perinitza Ensemble. The Moldavian Folk Theater scenario was created in 1964 for the Ciocîrlia Ensemble.
  - Dance Notes, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 28/181-182)
    Draft of introduction to unpublished volume describing 200 folk dances from Olt, Muntenia region (in Romanian). Handwritten and typewritten by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz, based on research conducted 1966-1972.
  - Ephemera
    - Show programs, 1938-1974 (Box-folder 29/183-184)
      Miscellaneous programs of performances in Romania and elsewhere of the Perinitza Ensemble and other groups that feature choreographic works by Gheorghe and Eugenia Popescu-Judetz. In Romanian, Turkish, French, German, and English.
    - Show programs, Tamburitzans, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 29/185-188)
      Performance programs of the Duquesne University Tamburitzans, 35th to 43rd seasons. Arranged chronologically. Includes choreographic works by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz.
    - Publicity, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 29/189)
      Photocopies of news clippings documenting the international activities of Eugenia Popescu-Judetz and the Perinitza Ensemble. In English, Finnish, French, and Turkish.
    - Printed music (Box-folder 29/190)
      The music was used by the Popescu-Judetzes in workshops where they taught folk dances to teachers from folk art schools and to amateur choreographers.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Album jackets and sheet music covers (Box-folder 29/191-192)
      Photocopies of published album jackets and sheet music covers of Romanian folk dance music. Original materials transferred to Recorded Sound Division.
    - Album notes (Box-folder 29/193)
      Photocopies of portions of the booklets accompanying "Antologia Muzicii Populare Romanesti" (trans., Anthology of Romanian Folk Music), volumes one and two. Describes folk instruments, songs, dances, and customs in English. Original discs and booklets transferred to Recorded Sound Division.
    - Costume collection, Kent State University (Box-folder 29/194-195)
      Accession reports and inventory lists from the Kent State University Museum collection of costumes, artifacts, and photographs donated by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz. Includes items on long-term loan from the Duquesne University Tamburitzans' Popescu-Judetz Collection of Romanian Costumes and Artifacts. Also includes two copies of the brochure, "The Romanian Exhibition," published by the Kent State University Museum that contains photographs of costumes donated by Eugenia Popescu-Judetz.
    - Writings (Box-folder 29/201-202)
      Popescu-Judetz, Eugenia. “Disemic Features in the Romanian Folk Musical ‘Jienii.’” Jersey, Channel Islands: Dance Studies 17 (1993): 77-84. Dance notation used for article is in Folder 202. Popescu-Judetz, Eugenia. Sixty Folk Dances of Romania. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania: Duquesne University Tamburitzans, Institute of Folk Arts, 1979. GV1685.P67
  - Sound Recordings, 1950-1972, Thirty-three 5" original reels; three 6" original reels; two 6 and 3/4" original reels; thirteen 7" original reels; AFC 1990/022: SR1-SR48
    Original field recordings made by Gheorghe and Eugenia Popescu-Judetz. Arranged numerically in the collector's order. Listening copies are available in the Folklife Reading Room. See folders 9-11 for inventory or PDF copy of inventory.
  - Graphic Materials
    - Original prints, 117 original black-and-white photographic prints of various sizes and one color print; AFC 1990/022: P1-P118 (Box 30-32, 36-39)
      Photographed by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz and others. Arranged in rough chronological order in the following categories: fieldwork, Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz and Ciocîrlia Ensemble, portraits of Gheorghe and Eugenia Popescu-Judetz, series for sketches of the Doiul dance from Banat, and Eugenia Popescu-Judetz. See Folder 15 for inventory. Reference photographic prints and copy negatives are available.
    - Photocopies of original prints (Box 30, 32, 36, Folder 198-200)
  - Moving Images
    - Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz, in street clothes, demonstrating Brîul and Barbuncul dances, 1966, 1 reel, 8 mm, 100 ft., silent, black and white film; AFC 1990/022: MV6 (Box 33)
      Filmed by Marty Koenig in Dobrudja, Romania. Koenig later gave this copy of the film to Eugenia Popescu-Judetz.
    - Informants Liana Tircolea and Gheorghe Covaci, dressed in costume, demonstrate a couple dance, Suita de pe Somes, 1955, 1 reel, 16 mm, 55 ft., silent, black and white film; AFC 1990/022: MV7 (Box 33)
      Filmed by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz in Transylvania.
    - Various informants in costume, outdoor scenes, and panoramic views, 1955, 1 reel, 8 mm, 86 ft., silent, black and white film; AFC 1990/022: MV8 (Box 33)
      Filmed by Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz in Moldavia, Muntenia, and Oltenia.
- Series II: Oral History Interview with Eugenia Popescu-Judetz conducted by Michelle Forner, 1995
  - Manuscripts, March 28-30, 1995 (Box-folder 29/196)
    Questions, tape logs, and notes.
  - Sound Recordings, Nine audiocassettes; AFC 1990/022: SR49-SR57
  - Graphic Materials, One sheet of black and white 35 mm negatives (36 images), one 8 x 10" black and white contact sheet, and four black and white 8 x 10" photographic prints (Box-folder 29/197)
  - Moving Images, Five videocassettes, hi8; AFC 1990/022: MV1-MV5
- Series III: 1997 Accrual
  - Dance Notation, Twenty-four files (Box 40-49, Folder 203-254)
    These dance notation files were added to the collection to complement the files in folders 33-156. The new files contain dance descriptions, dance typologies, field notes, and costume documentation. There is a folder on chants and lyrics from Strigaturi and an ethnography on the folk dances of Oltenia. New Years customs are documented here as well as folk theater from Moldavia. Included are monographic descriptions from the Bicaz, Muntenia, Moldavia, and Dobrdja region.
  - Dance Index
    - Listing 5, 397 pages (Box-folder 51/255-258)
      A list of the dance names from Moldavia, Pitra Neamt and Bacau areas and a dance dictionary/glossary from the Bicaz area.
    - Listing 6, 400 pages (Box-folder 51/259-262)
      Dance names and repertoire from Muntenia, Dobrudja, and Oltenia and a dance glossary of Briul.
    - Listing 7, 257 pages (Box-folder 51/263-264)
      Dance dictionaries from Dobrudja and Banat, repertoire lists from Banat, and dance glossaries from Muntenia and Arges.
    - Listing 8, 236 pages (Box-folder 52/265-267)
      Dance dictionary of Banat dances and repertoire lists from Dobrudja and Muntenia.
    - Listing 9, 252 pages (Box-folder 52/268-270)
      Dance repertoire from Bacau area, Moldavia. This listing also contains indexes of names from Piatra Neamt, Moldavia and dance lists from North Moldavia.
    - Listing 10, 313 pages (Box-folder 52/271-274)
      Dance repertoire lists from Muntenia, Pitesti, Dambovita, Faurei, Olt, Vedea, and Teleajen regions. This listing also holds an index/glossary of dances from Galati area.
    - Listing 11, 101 pages (Box-folder 53/275)
      Dance dictionary from Dobrudja, dance name lists from South Transylvania, and dance lists from Oltenia and Olt areas of Muntenia.
    - Listing 12 (Box-folder 53/276-277)
      Index cards and repertoire lists from all regions.
    - Listing 13, 98 pages (Box-folder 53/278)
      Dance dictionary of the Bicaz area of Moldavia and graphs.
  - Ephemera
    - Publications (Box-folder 54/279)
      Dances, described and notated, published in the magazine Cultura Poporului and Indrumatorul. Originals and duplications.
    - Portfolio (Box-folder 54/280)
      Contains photographs, publicity, programs, and postcards.
    - Copies of printed materials (Box-folder 54/281)
    - Oversized materials (Box 55)
      Includes dance notations, dance index files, and ephemera
- Series IV: 2004-2011 Accruals
  - Manuscripts
    - Field notebooks with dance notation from all regions, 1960 (Box-folder 54/282)
    - Eugenia Popescu-Judetz, Three Comparative Essays on Turkish Music, published by Pan Yayincilik, 2010 (Box-folder 54/283)
    - Musical postcards (Box-folder 54/284)
    - Index cards, 1885, 33 envelopes (Box 56)
      Contains information on dance names, instruments, seasonal customs, rituals, weddings, costumes, clothing, objects, tools and games, from Muntenia, Moldavia, Oltenia, Banat, and Transylvania regions. Collected by the linguist Bogdan Petriceicu Hasdeu. His complete collection is housed at the Library of Romanian Academy.
  - Artifacts
    - Plaque, 1989 (Box 57)
      Presented to Eugenia Popescu-Judetz in 1989 in memory of Gheorghe Popescu-Judetz for his lifelong dedication to Romanian Folk Dance from the Duquesne University Tamburitzans.